<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2019-02-13T13:32:37-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Purva Tendulkar</title><subtitle>MS CS Student at Georgia Tech
</subtitle><author><name>Purva Tendulkar</name><email>purva.tendulkar@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Applying for MS in the US</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/06/08/ms-apply/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Applying for MS in the US" /><published>2018-06-08T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-06-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/06/08/ms-apply</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/06/08/ms-apply/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;DISCLAIMER&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;These are purely my opinions and what helped me in my applications. Inferences made are based on my personal experiences and the admits and rejects that I got. FYI, I will be joining Georgia Tech for Masters in Computer Science in Fall 2018.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My admits (all MS CS) : GaTech, UPenn, UC San Diego, UCLA, USC&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My rejects (all MS CS) : Stanford, UT Austin, UMD College Park, UIUC, UNC Chapel Hill&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;building-your-cvprofile&quot;&gt;Building Your CV/Profile&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most students realize in the middle of their third year that they want to apply for MS, and immediately start fussing over how to build a good CV for it. It is important to understand that you cannot build a CV overnight. But consistent grades in relevant subjects, completed and working projects (with the sourcecode available on GitHub along with a well-written README) and extra projects (other than course projects or in the form of internships) are good ways to show that you have utilized the 4 years of your undergraduate life well. Of course, it is important that this information be compiled coherently in a CV. Since there is no standard format format for CVs, it is important that you take your time finding (or building a good template) in LaTeX. Your CV is your technical selling point so make sure that it is well-written. Sell yourself well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;actually-writing-your-cv&quot;&gt;Actually writing your CV&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DO not lie. Overly impressive achievements arouse suspicion, and if not backed up with grades, LoRs or credible sources, they will only act as a deterrent. Be honest. Refrain from mentioning papers published in random (possibly blacklisted) conferences. Rather, refrain from publishing in such conferences or journals altogether. Mentions of such papers will only act negatively on your application so only mention them if they have been published in reputed conferences. Don’t worry if your CV doesn’t have a huge list of awards or isn’t more than 1-2 pages. Rather, shorter but well-written CVs are appreciated better. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jeanqasaur/academic-application-materials/blob/master/phd-application-2007/jean_yang_resume.pdf&quot;&gt;Jean Yang’s CV&lt;/a&gt; is a good reference for this. You can also choose to be creative and go for something cool like &lt;a href=&quot;https://pjreddie.com/static/Redmon%20Resume.pdf&quot;&gt;Joseph Redmon’s resume&lt;/a&gt;. This might be a little risky and you should be super confident of your skills to make something like this. Of course on the bright side, it shows creativity and actually looks really cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important thing to keep in mind is not to mention too many achievements of your school days in your CV. Unless they are exceptional achievements like national/international level scholarships, Olympiad wins or something of that calibre, they will not be very useful in proving how good a student you have been in the last 4+ years. For example, quiz winner in an inter-school event or house captain are not really worth mentioning, especially the latter since you are applying for graduate studies in a technical field, not a management course. Of course it doesn’t hurt to be an all-rounder, but be sure to choose the content in your CV carefully as it will reflect what you consider to be your biggest achievements. If house captain was considered big enough to make it to your CV, it might reflect negatively on your application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;job-experience--useful-or-not&quot;&gt;Job Experience : Useful or not?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have noticed many students deciding to work in a company for a couple of years before applying. These are some common reasons cited for the same-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financial reasons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Uncertainty of future plans&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hope that job experience will help improve one’s chances of getting accepted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the first reason is perfectly valid, I strongly believe that reasons 2 and 3 only make sense if you plan to take up a job where you will get to do work relevant to your higher education goals. So in that case, working in a startup or a smaller company would be a better option for honing your technical skills rather than a large, multinational corporation or bank (this is a little specific to CS students for work in India). In most large companies, you will have little control over the kind of projects to which you are assigned, at least in the first one year. Of course if you are getting the opportunity to work in a top research lab like MSR, it is worth considering. But for the most part, you are required to stay in the company for sufficient time and slowly work your way up to larger and more involved projects, which is not practical if you are strongly considering graduate studies. And if you plan on applying just one year later, that leaves you with only 2-3 months of job experience at the time of your applications which is hardly useful. The only major advantage that I see for applying after final year would be the fact that you can showcase your final year thesis (B.Tech project) in your application (which is a significant 2 semester long project). It also leaves you with some extra time for writing a paper, which if successful, will be a huge plus on your application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So does job experience help at all for MS applications? Well, for the most part, I would have to say no. The major reason being that most universities in the US seem to value research experience more than job experience. This means that an application with good research internships and/or a paper with strong LoRs to support it, is looked upon more than one with a few months spent in a company. A problem which arises when you work in a company is when you have to gather your letters of recommendation (an extremely and arguably, the most important material in your application). Most universities do not prefer (or in some cases do not accept) recommendation letters from industry supervisors, and require that your recommenders be professors who have taught you course subjects or under whom you have completed research projects. If it has been more than 1-2 years since your graduation, it is diffcult to contact and approach former professors for LoRs and the letters may not be as impactful. In that case, in order to improve your chances of getting into a top school for Masters, a better option would be to work as a an RA (Research Assistant) under a faculty member, instead of taking up a job. This gives you more time-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to work hands-on in your field of interest&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;explore opportunities in your field of interest and make a more informed decision about your reason for pursuing graduate studies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;get enough time to work dedicatedly on a research project and attempt at publishing a paper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;get a strong and more relevant recommendation letter to vouch for your skills and preparation for graduate studies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;NOTE : MS CS programs in universities like UIUC and UNC are known to be more research oriented, in that, they see Masters students as potential researchers. So having a research background is even more important to these universities.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-start--choosing-colleges&quot;&gt;How to Start : Choosing Colleges&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now that you’ve made up your mind that you will be applying for Masters, typically the first step is deciding which universities to apply to. Most students don’t put much thought into this and simply end up referring to a ranking website. Or sometimes seek help from external paid sources for this process who will evaluate their profile and give them a list of colleges “right” for them. What is even more shocking is that these agencies even write SoPs for students. Here are some problems with this-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A outsider can never accurately asses your knowledge or skills in your area of interest or determine which universities are right for you. There is actually no deterministic way to do so. Not to sound preachy, but you are your best judge.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paid professionals are only interested in showing a higher percentage of students getting accepted into US universities. In this process they end up recommending “safer” options rather than more ambitious choices.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paid professionals often use metrics like GPA, GRE score and internships (assessing you simply based on where you did your internship rather than what you did there).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This dependency keeps you completely detached from the entire process without knowledge about what you’re getting into, and not to mention the hefty fees that come along with these counselling sessions. And this is absolutely unnecessary given that all the information is already available on the official websites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So coming back, how do you choose universities? Well, it depends on what your future goals are. There are usually 2 broad goals - 1) Intention of getting a good job at the end of 2 years, 2) Intention of exploring research during Masters and applying for a PhD later. It is important that you take some time to think about which of these 2 options you wish to choose. The factors to be taken in account while selecting a college are then as follows-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Job Goal : Reputation of the program (along with reputation of the university), job placement statistics, location, TA/RA opportunities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research Goal : Number of professors in your field of interest who are actively publishing, research output of that university in your field of interest, number of research groups and whether they are actively hiring Masters students, variety of courses offered in your field of interest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;NOTE : The location factor is a little debatable. While many say that location is important for helping you get internships (and eventually jobs), many also say that since the internship and job application process is all online, it hardly matters where your university is geographically located.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The job goal factors are pretty straightforward, but those with research goals need to work a little harder. The information is often not directly available. Here are some tips to go about finding it-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check out the websites of faculty members in your area of interest. See the kind of work they’re doing, number of Masters and PhD students in their groups, etc. Their websites are usually pretty up-to-date.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every area has some known reputed conferences. Check out which universities seem to be actively publishing in these conferences in the last 4-5 years.
For Computer Science students, &lt;a href=&quot;http://csrankings.org/&quot;&gt;csrankings&lt;/a&gt; gives a good indication of research output of the university.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides this, there are a number of personal factors like weather, how expensive the program is, how near/far you will be from dear ones. But from an academic perspective, the above list covers the main ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, one of the most important factors is : “What are the odds of me getting into XYZ program in XYZ university”? I used the following factors for this-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acceptance rates (this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/What-are-the-admission-statistics-for-top-schools-in-computer-science-information-science-and-computer-engineering&quot;&gt;Quora&lt;/a&gt; answer is a good starting point for this information)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My relative standing in my undergraduate university (in terms of grades/GPA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How unique and exciting my projects and internships had been&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trying to compare points 1, 2, 3 with the profiles of my seniors and analysing the admits and rejects that they got&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These, along with the factors specific to future goals, should be sufficient to decide your colleges. This kind of groundwork is extremely important and is often overlooked by many students. Start working on this early (at least 2-3 months before you actually start applying). Make a Google sheet and keep updating it with this information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, how many universities should you be applying to? Well, I would suggest no more than 10-12. Choose your universities wisely and work hard on each of them, rather than applying to too many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thought - People often say : “You’re smart. You will stand out no matter where you go.” I don’t completely agree with this. While hardwork and intelligence are required to succeed, if you want have a specific goal that you want to reach, it also requires&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;proper research and planning&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;gathering different opinions by reading online, talking to a lot of people, and then&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;making informed decisions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t just choose a university because it was your childhood dream and it is fancy. Be practical. Decide your goals. Prioritize.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Purva Tendulkar</name><email>purva.tendulkar@gmail.com</email></author><category term="blogs" /><summary type="html">DISCLAIMER - These are purely my opinions and what helped me in my applications. Inferences made are based on my personal experiences and the admits and rejects that I got. FYI, I will be joining Georgia Tech for Masters in Computer Science in Fall 2018.</summary></entry></feed>